Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, we're going to start today. We pick
up with ע"ד Ayin-Daled where דף ה, daf heh, and it's the
next משנה, Mishnah, and we are still dealing
with the, you know, unusual cases, the ones that don't happen like
the standard case of the תורה, Torah, but the most curious or
interesting cases that the פרק perek decided to focus on: the case
of the father and the ארוס arus and the groom who are
both in partnership in all the vows. And now we turn to
a case which we touched on yesterday, and that is the one
of the שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. And what is the role of
the יבם? yavam? On the one hand, it's a carry over of
the marriage of the dead brother, and that might have even been
נשואין. nesu'in. It could have been אירוסין, erusin, but it might have
been נשואין. nesu'in. It requires less, you know, intent to materialize it,
to actualize it into a full נשואין. nesu'in. Sex even done without,
you know, without any כוונה kavanah to create נשואין nesu'in or whatever
does it because of the זיקה, zika, you know, and of the
remnant of the קידושין kiddushin or the transfer of the relationship that
now exists between the wife and her brother-in-law that was transferred from
her dead husband. And on the other hand, right now, the nature
of the relationship is not the same as קידושין, kiddushin, because if,
for example, she were to go ahead and be with another man,
it would not be adulterous, it would not be אשת איש. eshet
ish. Why? And you could do חליצה, chalitzah, which is much like
seemingly less of a procedure, now they make it so complicated. But
anyway, you
know, instead of a גט, get, right? So is the
יבם
yavam
in a position, is he needed, and does he have the ability
to be part of the הפרה hafara together with the father? So
that's the question. So let's take a look at the
משנה.
Mishnah.
שומרת יבם, Shomeret yavam, so a woman who is waiting ייבום. yibum.
בין יבם אחד בין שני יבמין, Bein yavam echad bein shnei yevamin,
whether she has two brothers-in-law or one brother-in-law. Two brothers-in-law is obviously
more confusing because then who is the one who has, you can't
designate any particular one as the one who's in the relationship with
her? He's in... well, thinking, that's what we're going to figure out.
רבי אליעזר אומר יפר. Rabbi Eliezer omer yafir. Rabbi Eliezer says he
can be מפר. mefir. You know, who is he if there are
two? So we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. Maybe either one of
them. Right, okay, but it's also יפר yafir is not just he
can be מפר, mefir, remember that unless there's a possibility here that
somebody considers it to be in the פרק, perek, in the category
of נשואין, nesu'in, it would mean he can only be מפר mefir
together with the father. So, well actually, let me take a step
back and say the following. He was obviously already married, because now
there's a case of ייבום. yibum. If her marriage to the first
guy was נשואין, nesu'in, then the father isn't in the picture at
all. And the only question now is, and then the question would
be, does the יבם yavam consider like נשואין? nesu'in? Okay, because if
it was only considered like אירוסין, erusin, then the יבם yavam would
not be in a position to do anything. אירוסין Erusin without father
is not in a position to do anything. But we're going to
be assuming, I mean, we're going to assume both possibilities, but we're
going to be assuming also the case where she only had אירוסין
erusin with the guy, with her husband who now died. So now
the father remains in the picture. So if that's true, it might
be sufficient that the relationship with the יבם yavam is similar to
that of אירוסין. erusin. Okay, right, because as long as the father
remains in the picture, אירוסין erusin relationship gives the husband the right
to be part of the הפרה. hafara. But here's the question whether
יפר yafir means, if it's the marriage was אירוסין erusin and the
father's still in the picture, and יפר yafir means that it's like
אירוסין, erusin, then all יפר yafir doesn't mean that his הפרה hafara
ends the story, it means his הפרה hafara is necessary. Right, because
if there's a father still, you need the father and the groom.
So יפר yafir doesn't mean oh he can be מפר mefir and
we're done, it means he needs to be מפר mefir together with
the father. Okay, it actually complicates things, doesn't make it easier for
it to be הופר. hufar. If however it's like נשואין, nesu'in, right,
or she's already outside the control of her father, but whatever, either
way it's like נשואין, nesu'in, then יפר yafir means he does it
alone. So there's a big question what יפר yafir means in the
משנה. Mishnah. Does it mean it's like נשואין nesu'in and he does
it alone and then it's the end of the story, or does
יפר yafir mean that it's like the יבם yavam relationship is like
אירוסין erusin and he's יפר yafir together with the father. Okay, but
Rabbi Eliezer basically says one of those, whether one or two יבמין,
yevamin, they are in some type of a position to do הפרה,
hafara, either like an ארוס arus or like a בעל. ba'al. רבי
יהושע אומר לאחד אבל לא לשניים. Rabbi Yehoshua omer l'echad aval lo
l'shnayim. That only works if there's one יבם. yavam. If there are
two יבמין, yevamin, then they're not, because you don't know who. Okay,
now, well we'll see, but because we'll discuss that in the גמרא,
Gemara, but presumably they both can't, because anybody, it's not like one
of them is and we don't know which one, right? It's that
because it's indeterminate fundamentally, at its base, indeterminate, no... nobody is in
a real relationship with her. Okay. It's an indeterminate relationship, not that
one person is definitely in a relationship but we just don't know
which of them. Okay. So therefore neither of them are in the
position. Now, presumably neither of them are in the position means that
if there is a father, the father does it by himself. It
doesn't mean like you're stuck. You could imagine like they're stuck. Well,
you're the father, there is a husband, we don't know which one
is the husband, so we're stuck. No, the whole point is that
because there's it's indeterminate, nobody gets to play the role of the
husband and therefore the father does it by himself. Okay. But if
there is only one, then yes, then he is in that role.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, I'm sorry, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva.
אומר—לא לאחד ולא לשניים, even if there's only one, he does not
have any status. And it's all the father, if it's a case
of a father. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, מה, mah, I
don't get it, he says to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva מה אישה
שקנה הוא לעצמו הרי הוא מיפר נדריה, Mah isha shekana hu l'atzmo
harei hu meifer nedareha,
when a man marries a woman by himself, he's in a position
to be part of the הפרה. hafarah. אישה שהקנו לו מן השמיים,
Isha shehiknu lo min hashamayim,
when heaven has given it to her, to her to him, which
basically means like, you know, it's not even arbitrary, it's not even,
you know, God wants it, it's defined by, you know, by הלכה,
halakha, by heaven. So if God wants this relationship, that seems to
be the logic,
אינו דין שייפר נדריה, eino din sheyaifer nedareha, how much more so
should, you know, you might want to even add like there's a
מצווה mitzvah to do יבום yibum and all these types of things.
That should be an indication that it's a stronger relationship, and he
should have, how much more so should he be in a right
to do הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. Now, you could question that very
thing, you know, but you understand the idea within those concepts of
the world of יבום yibum and, you know, יקום שם אחיו המת,
yakum shem achiv hamet, etc. Once this is a situation, it's like
the Torah really wants this relationship to happen. So how much more
so should you be in that position? אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar
lo Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said back, no, no, I
don't buy the comparison. אם אמרת באישה שקנה הוא לעצמו, Im amarta
b'isha shekana hu l'atzmo, if he marries a woman on his own,
שאין לאחרים בה רשות, she'ein l'acherim bah reshus,
there's only him and her, nobody else is involved. תאמר באישה שהקנו
לו מן השמיים, Tomar b'isha shehiknu lo min hashamayim, in the case
here by יבום yibum when it's all done by heaven, שיש לאחרים
בה רשות, sheyesh l'acherim bah reshus, there's somebody else involved, there's the
other brother-in-law. Okay, in the case of two brother-in-laws. So at least
in case of two brother-in-laws, this is not a better situation
since other somebody else can go ahead and do the יבום yibum
for each one of them, they don't have the same type of
relationship. It's not a type of an exclusive relationship, and you know,
it doesn't particularly designate them. It could be somebody else. Okay. So
therefore that in a case of two brother-in-laws it's not, you know,
clearly, they're not in a strong position. ואמר לו רבי יהושע, V'amar
lo Rabbi Yehoshua, but then רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said back,
עקיבא פרצת
בשני יבמים, Akiva peratzta b'shnei yevamim, that's good when there are two
brothers, two brother-in-laws. מה אתה משיב על יבם אחד, Mah atah meshiv
al yevam echad, what do you answer on one brother-in-law? Then רבי
אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's קל וחומר kal v'chomer makes sense. Then רבי אליעזר'ס
Rabbi Eliezer's קל וחומר kal v'chomer makes sense, right? Because then if
this is a divinely mandated type of or, you know, created זיקה
zika and a divinely mandated act of יבום, yibum, he should be
in a stronger position. Okay. So what do you say if there's
only one brother-in-law? אמר לו, רבי עקיבא amar lo Rabbi Akiva, said
back, אין היבמה גמורה ליבם כשם שארוסה גמורה לאישה. Ein hayevamah gemurah
layevam k'shem she'arusah gemurah l'isha. No, even if there's only one brother-in-law,
the יבמה yevamah is not fully given over to the יבם yevam
the same way the ארוסה arusah is given over to her husband.
What does that mean? So there's a difference. We can think about
right about adultery. It's not considered an act of adultery. It's an
איסור issur of לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה, lo tihiyeh eishet hamet
hachutza, but it's not considered the nature of relationship is not as
weighty. Okay. It's not marriage, it's not as weighty of a relationship,
and therefore I'm sorry, even one brother-in-law is not in that position.
Okay. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא רבי עקיבא סבר אין זיקה. Bi-shlama Rabbi Akiva savar
ein zika. So we get it. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds that
there's no זיקה. zika. Now זיקה, zika, you all might remember from
יבמות, Yevamot, is—I
mean everything he says, right? There's something there that can be that
has to be like actualized for the act of יבום yibum done.
But to identify and say יש זיקה, yesh zika, that means like
we actually give that potential some real weight and say that it's
like something, so you know, that there's a
real relationship. There's a real bond there that really defines some concrete
relationship. It's not just some potential waiting to be actualized. Somehow there
is actually some actual relationship that already exists. Okay. So that's and
that has various נפקא מינה. nafka minas. So basically it's saying well
one way to conceptualize this debate, you know, you could have said
everybody says יש זיקה, yesh zika, but still it's not strong enough
to be a case of אשת איש eshet ish and adultery. It's
not strong enough to play the role of a father, right? You
could have said that. Fine, there's זיקה, zika, but still not like
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says at the end, at the level of
קידושין. kiddushin. It might be something, but it's you know it's not
it's not the same weight. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara wants to
conceptualize it this way. The easiest way to understand is that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva doesn't really recognize the זיקה zika any concrete relationship
yet. Yes there's a מצווה, mitzvah, yes there's an איסור issur of
לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה, lo tihiyeh eishet hamet hachutza, all those
types of things. But it hasn't yet defined itself, it's more like
a potential and an obligation rather than a real concrete relationship and
therefore he's not in a position to do הפרה. hafarah. Now that's
interesting because if memory serves, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the one
that says יש ממזר מחייבי לאוין yesh mamzer m'chayei lavin and that
a woman who commits who meets up with another man and who's
awaiting יבום, yibum, the child is a ממזר. mamzer. I'm pretty sure,
I should double check. But anyway, so that would be funny to
say that side by side with the idea of יש זיקה או
אין זיקה, yesh zika o ein zika, but okay, maybe that's just
a position about like you know I mean there could be like
there's an איסור, issur, there's other איסורי לאוין issurei lavin in the
תורה Torah that could, you know, create ממזר mamzer that are not
about the bond of the concrete bond between the husband and the
wife. So whatever you say about the world of ממזרות, mamzeirus, he's
saying this is not a concrete bond yet between these two parties
and therefore he's not in a position to do הפרה. hafarah. Thank
you so much. Okay.
Hmm,
well that's good. Okay, so ואלא, v'ella, so that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. It's not a concrete bond. אלא, ella, רבי אליעזר רבי יהושע
סבר, Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Yehoshua savar, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is of
the
position יש זיקה. yesh zika. There is a זיקה zika and
therefore there is a concrete bond, he can do הפרה, hafarah, but
if there's two it's it's obvious why it doesn't work because nobody
says that there's זיקה zika where there's two because then you don't
know where's the זיקה, zika, right? It's fundamentally indeterminate. אלא רבי אליעזר
מאי טעמא, ella Rabbi Eliezer mai ta'ama, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
even with two, what's his logic?
אי יש זיקה אין ברירה, ei yesh zika ein b'reirah, even if
there's זיקה zika you can't determine which one is the one, right?
I mean I guess you could say well but now you know
if it's funny to assert though you could say well maybe you
know a year from now when one of them does יבום yibum
then retroactively we will say he was the one with the זיקה
zika then, but if that were true he should have said it,
right? So it seems like even if in the end they both
do חליצה chalitzah or something, you know? So what's the logic? Right
now it's fundamentally indeterminate, why does any one of them in a
position to do
הפרה? hafarah? So אמר רבי אמי, amar Rabbi Ami, כגון שעשה מאמר,
k'gon she'asa ma'amar, he makes an אוקימתא ukeimta in the משנה mishnah
and he says you're right. In a basic case where there were
two and then obviously none of them would be in a position.
But what happened is one of them did מאמר. ma'amar. You might
remember from מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamot that מאמר ma'amar is when one
of the brother-in-laws goes ahead and does an act of קידושין kiddushin
with the sister-in-law. Now that act of קידושין kiddushin does not make
her מקודשת, mekudeshet, well we'll see in a minute the בית שמאי,
Beis Shammai, I think according to the general assumption, does not make
her מקודשת, mekudeshet, does not make her his his his, it's fundamentally
there's only one real path that works by by יבום. yibum. Either
sex to make it to make it into a marriage, or חליצה
chalitzah to undo it. גט get doesn't do anything דאורייתא d'Oraita and
קידושין kiddushin doesn't do anything דאורייתא. d'Oraita. But the rabbis said if
you can do קידושין kiddushin as a way of basically showing like
calling you know dibs, as a sorry to use that terminology anyway,
but like basically say like A demonstrating your intent and B sort
of closing out you know the option for the other brothers. Okay,
if there's more than one brother. Actually it's more than that because
you know חז"ל Chazal basically from when you remember when we learned
יבמות Yevamot even if there's only one brother wanted him to do
קידושין kiddushin first. They wanted him to sort of you know you
don't want to just like go straight to the sex, right? You
want to sort of you know show something that shows like intent
and structure and whatever for the relationship and then you have that
the act of sex which is the act of יבום. yibum. So
חז"ל Chazal actually wanted that to be part of the process even
if there's only one brother, but that's the idea of מאמר. ma'amar.
So if there are two brothers and one does מאמר, ma'amar, then
that basically designates him in the position to do the יבום. yibum.
And that's what allows him to do it and not the other.
And therefore the debate between רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer would be a case where there's מאמר ma'amar where רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's enough to put him in the position
to do to do הפרה hafarah to designate him. And רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says no fundamentally even after מאמר ma'amar another brother could
jump in and do the יבום yibum and it doesn't really fully
prevent the other brother from doing it even though he shouldn't and
therefore it still remains not non that מאמר ma'amar is not enough
to give this person that role.
Wait I'm sorry. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was saying so
because when I looked at the משנה mishnah you know it seemed
to me that the שומרת יבם shomeret yavam for two brothers any
one of them can do right?
But the גמרא Gemara is not happy with that.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying no it's not really anyone
it's one of them did מאמר. ma'amar. We're talking about a case
where someone did מאמר. ma'amar. Not פשט peshat in the משנה mishnah
no question not פשט peshat in the משנה. mishnah. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא ella says the גמרא Gemara
says like this
ורבי אליעזר v'Rabbi Eliezer now it's not enough to just סתם stam
say you did מאמר ma'amar because again מאמר ma'amar doesn't have any
weight according in the תורה Torah it's only like rabbinic. So why
would that be sufficient to give a person the power to do
הפרה? hafarah? So the גמרא Gemara says רבי אליעזר סבר לה כבית
שמאי Rabbi Eliezer savar lah k'Beis Shammai because he also holds like
בית שמאי Beis Shammai דאמרי מאמר קונה קנין גמור d'amri ma'amar koneh
kinyan gamur that בית שמאי Beis Shammai actually says that מאמר ma'amar
really does something even according to the תורה. Torah. What would be
an example of that? So if you take a look at the
ר"ן Ran he he spells it out he says On the
next page
actually.
Okay,
yeah, turn the page to the ר"ן. Ran. He says, מאמר קונה
קנין גמור, maamar koneh kinyan gamur, it's like four lines down in
the narrow lines, דהויא ליה ככנוסה ומפטר לה בגיטא ולא בעי חליצה,
de-hava lei ke-knusa u-mifetar la be-gita v'lo ba-ei chalitza, that it really
does so much consequence that, now we're going to see in a
minute, it might not be enough consequence that if she sleeps with
another man it's אשת איש, eishes ish, okay, that might not be.
But it does enough to actually create, now there actually is this
track, well, he married her, he did
קידושין. kiddushin.
So now he's sort of moved her away from the יבום yibum
track and put her on this more traditional קידושין kiddushin track. And
as such, if he changes his mind and doesn't want to be
married to her, he doesn't have to do חליצה. chalitza. You can
actually now do גט. get. Right?
That's not what we said, right, in that way? Well, just do,
just do מאמר maamar and then what's the problem that it's hard
to figure out how to do חליצה? chalitza?
Yeah, alright, whatever. Anyway, how we do it. Anyway, fine. So בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says that the מאמר maamar actually has some real
דאורייתא de-oraisa weight. If it allows you now to do a גט
get instead of חליצה, chalitza, then that means that it has really
defined the relationship. Okay. Now it might not be a full קידושין.
kiddushin. And we're going to see in a minute whether there's still
some other ways that it gets derailed. But even if it's not
a full קידושין, kiddushin, if it really has now allowed for a
different type of a מעשה, maaseh, now you do גט get instead
of חליצה chalitza and so on, then that really now defines the
relationship in a very concrete way. And if that relationship has been
defined in a concrete way, then this, even though there are two
brother-in-laws, the one that did מאמר maamar can do הפרה. hafara. Okay,
that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds.
And where were we? רבי אליעזר כבית שמאי דאמר מאמר קונה
קנין גמור. Rabbi Eliezer k'Beis Shammai d'amar maamar koneh kinyan gamur. רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua אמר לך, amar lach, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would
say back, הני מילי בחד יבם. hani mili b'chad yabam. That would
be good if there's only one יבם yabam then you wouldn't even
need מאמר. maamar. אבל בשני יבמים לא, aval b'shnei yevamim lo, but
not with two יבמים. yevamim. Even if there's מאמר, maamar, why? מי
קמידי דכי אתי אחוהי אסר ליה בביאה או בגיטא
ומפיק. mi ka-midi d'ki asi achei asar lei b'via o b'gita u-mafik.
Is there any scenario where the brother could come along and even
after מאמר, maamar, the brother could come along and do ביאה? bia?
Okay, מאמר maamar again, it doesn't, it's a funny position of בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. It's קונה קנין גמור, koneh kinyan gamur, but it
still isn't יבום yibum hasn't taken place yet. And it doesn't still
close out the other brother. And if the other brother were to
come along and do יבום yibum it actually would work and then
this guy would have to give a גט, get, he wouldn't be
able to finish the marriage with this woman even though you did
מאמר, maamar, okay, or if the other brother even gave her a
גט, get, he could go ahead and make her forbidden to you,
you the guy who did מאמר. maamar. So because the other brother
is still involved, even if you've actually created something really concrete, it's
still not exclusive. You haven't closed out your other brother. Okay? And
since you haven't closed out your other brother, even though there's something
concrete here, you're not in enough of a
relationship, it's not
exclusive, even if concrete it's not exclusive and you're not in a
position to do הפרה. hafara. Okay so that's the debate. Is מאמר
maamar sufficient even within בית שמאי Beis Shammai and even with this
idea of קנין גמור kinyan gamur to designate to put one brother
in the position to be able to do הפרה. hafara. רבי עקיבא
סבר אין זיקה. Rabbi Akiva savar ein zika. And then רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva like we said, he just doesn't endorse any of this.
Even with מאמר, maamar, even with all of that, no, there's no
real concrete relationship here. Okay. ורבי אלעזר דאמר מאמר לבית שמאי אין
קונה אלא לדחות בצרה. v'Rabbi Elazar d'amar maamar l'Beis Shammai ein koneh
ela lidchos b'tzara. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to clarify, right,
what this means,
I'm sorry. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to clarify that even
within בית שמאי Beis Shammai we might not be able to say
קונה קנין גמור. koneh kinyan gamur. That was the one thing that
allowed us to understand how it could work according to רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. But there's a רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, a little bit
confusing here. The משנה Mishnah is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but now
there's a רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar position that within בית שמאי Beis
Shammai that narrows
the scope of what בית שמאי Beis Shammai means. So אם יאמר,
im yomar, so we have a position of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
that says that לבית שמאי אין קונה אלא לדחות בצרה, l'Beis Shammai
ein koneh ela lidchos b'tzara, that מאמר maamar is not really קונה.
koneh.
So this is wrong, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer here, right?
Right, it should be if you look at the side it says
אלעזר. Elazar. Okay. So meaning, all מאמר maamar does, you're mistaken. Your
desire to identify with בית שמאי Beis Shammai this idea that מאמר
maamar is קונה קנין גמור koneh kinyan gamur that really isn't the
position of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position really
is that מאמר maamar just prevents him from having to deal with
the sister one. What does this mean? Everybody, does everybody long for
the days of learning יבמות? Yevamos? Has everybody seen the diagrams on
the board? So let's do it again.
Okay, so here you basically have three brothers, ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon,
and לוי. Levi. They're all brothers. Okay, and these two are married
to sisters, רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. Okay. Now,
שמעון Shimon dies.
Now
here's a
מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, he
goes ahead and he does the מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum and
then לוי Levi dies, שלום ישראל. Shalom Yisrael. He's already married to
the wife sister, can't, doesn't have any מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum
with לוי, Levi, right? But if he doesn't do the מצוה Mitzvah
of יבום Yibbum and לוי Levi dies, then he can't do the
מצוה Mitzvah of יבום Yibbum with either because each one is אחות
זקוקתו. achot zekukato. Everybody remember that? Okay. So because of the זיקה,
zikah, it's like he's quasi-married to each one and therefore to do
יבום yibbum with the other one, it's a quasi wife sister, right?
So if you hold זיקה.
zikah. Okay, let's not worry about that. Okay, so then what if,
however, before לוי Levi died, he did מאמר maamar with רחל? Rachel?
Okay? And now לוי Levi dies. Can he now say, "Oh, you
know, goodbye לאה, Leah, I'm already married to רחל," Rachel, right? "So
quasi-married to רחל, Rachel, so לאה Leah just walks away and I'm
going to finish it, and it's not אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato because
there's no זיקה zikah here because this has already been defined, right?"
Or do we say that מאמר maamar is only רבנן, Rabbanan, דאורייתא
de'oraita it's nothing and there's really still an equal זיקה zikah to
both, and therefore if he finishes, if he does ביאה biah with
רחל, Rachel, it's still אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato for לאה. Leah. That's
where the מחלוקת machloket is. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you
don't have to worry about לאה Leah because there's already מאמר. maamar.
Okay, so one way of understanding that is a very broad understanding:
for בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, מאמר maamar really makes it like they're
already married, and therefore it's אחות אשתו achot ishto and it's דוחה
doche over the זיקה. zikah. It has קנין גמור. kinyan gamur. But
there's a position of רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Eleazar. Says רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Eleazar, "No, don't take this beyond its narrow scope. All בית שמאי
Beit Shammai is saying is that the מאמר maamar gives enough to
keep לאה Leah out of the picture, okay? ודוחה צרה. vedoche tzarah.
It keeps לאה Leah out of the picture, okay? So maybe you
could say it makes it that there's not a זיקה zikah to
לאה Leah or something, but whatever it does, it does not mean
that in general the מאמר maamar fully makes it as if they're
married." Okay, so that's the question. That's the בית שמאי Beit Shammai
we start with. So if you say, read this בית שמאי Beit
Shammai in a very narrow, local way, we're back to the problem:
how can your act of מאמר maamar be enough to put you
in the position, you know, over your brother to say that you're
really in the position to do the הפרה hafarah and you're really
the one that has the relationship with this woman? Okay, so let's
read that.
ולרבי אלעזר דאמר מאמר לבית שמאי אינו קונה אלא לדחות את הצרה
בלבד. U'leRabbi Eleazar de'amar maamar leBeit Shammai eino koneh ela lidchot et
hatzarah bilvad. It's really, what's קונה? koneh? All it does is it
just keeps לאה Leah out of the picture. מאי איכא למימר? Mai
ika lemeimar? We're back to square one. There are two brothers.
Either one of them could do יבום. yibbum. We tried to say
that מאמר maamar makes it like it's a relationship with one according
to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but we're saying that no, there's a
read of בית שמאי Beit Shammai that even מאמר maamar doesn't really
do anything like that. So what makes it one brother over the
other? So הגמרא haGemara says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, what
are we talking about? כגון שעמד בדין kegon she-amad bedin ונתחייב לה
מזונות. venitchayev lah mezonot.
So here's the question, here's the case. The case is not just
מאמר. maamar. The case is that let's say, I don't know, one
of them was the older brother,
okay, and normally they turn to the older brother and expect him
to do יבום, yibbum, and he's been dilly-dallying, so they bring him
to a בית דין. Beit Din. And they basically tell the older
brother, "You've got to go ahead and do יבום." yibbum. But just
telling him that wouldn't do enough, right? Because again, that doesn't make
a concrete relationship and the other brother could always jump in and
do it. But then the בית דין Beit Din says, "Look, she's
been waiting a year for you to do יבום. yibbum. As long
as she's continuing to wait for you to get your act together,
you're going to have to start paying her food bills," okay? ונתחייב
לה מזונות, venitchayev lah mezonot, sort of right? Because the limit is
this woman doesn't have a husband anymore, she should have been married.
It's sort of like she's waiting for the נישואין nissu'in more than
a year. He has to start paying מזונות. mezonot. So now, even
though halachically there's not a concrete relationship yet, the בית דין Beit
Din has now obligated him to pay מזונות. mezonot. Now, הוא כמאן
דנתחייב לה מזונות, hu k'man d'nitchayev lah mezonot, וכי הא דרבי פנחס
ve-ki ha d'Rabbi Pinchas and this follows Rabbi Pinchas that we quoted
yesterday, משמיה דרבא mishmeih de'Rava דאמר כל הנודרת על דעת בעלה היא
נודרת. de'amar kol hanoderet al da'at ba'alah hi noderet. That
even though halachically there is not yet a concrete enough relationship, she's
doing it, a woman has in mind the man who is going
to, who she's going to be living with, and once he's paying
for her food bills, she sees herself as in future living with
this guy even though halachically that has not yet been defined. And
therefore her vows are considered to be presumed that he's okay, על
דעתו. al da'ato. Now again, I want to remind you of the
very important conceptual points the ר"ן Ran made yesterday. What the ר"ן
Ran said, it doesn't just mean like this could work with any
guy off the street. Like if somebody says, comes and says, I
don't know, let's say her sister, let's not even make it a
man, her rich sister came along and said, "You know what? Don't
worry, I'm going to come ahead and I'm going to pay your
food bills" or something for you, right? Where somebody explicitly said, "I'm
doing this נדר neder על דעת al da'at so-and-so," okay? You know,
if I don't explicitly say בתנאי bitnai that he says "okay", then
על דעת al da'at doesn't really, the ר"ן Ran says, doesn't mean
anything. It can't stop her from being good. You know, and we're
talking within And we're talking within normal הלכות, halachos, we're not saying,
you know, there has to be an act of הפרה, hafara, it
has to be the right language, it has to be within 24
hours. What this means, says the ר"ן, Ran, is you take somebody
that's already a quasi-husband.
Who's a quasi-husband? First of all, the ארוס, arus, the groom, yesterday,
or here the יבם. yavam. And you say if you add to
that person who's already quasi a husband,
the reality that he's paying the food bill and she sees herself
in the relationship with him and about to be married to him,
then that would fit in the Torah's category of the בעל. ba'al.
Okay, the בעל ba'al doesn't have to be formally exactly the בעל.
ba'al. There are other things that are close enough that already it's
a husband relationship plus other important elements that make it in the
Torah's category of the... in millions of דאורייתא de'oraisa category of the
בעל. ba'al.
And he did a מאמר, ma'amar, right, in this case?
It could be also did a מאמר, ma'amar, either way you've certainly
designated him over the other brothers to be the one to keep
her.
So they would automatically designate the older brother.
Yeah, the normal thing would be to go to the older brother.
Okay, right. So basically what he is saying is that you're right,
it's still a problem there are two brothers, but because each brother,
they're not strangers, there is a יבום, yibum, there is a זיקה,
zika, even though it's indeterminate who, but combined with the fact of
her psychological state and the reality that he's paying the bills, that
makes him in the category of the בעל, ba'al, and that makes
him in the position to be מפר. meifer. Now the ר"ן Ran
says the פשט pshat of that is by the way, remember we
used that language yesterday to put the groom in the position like
after נשואין, nisuin, that he did it by himself, if you remember
that yesterday, right? Once you're paying מזונות, mezonos, that's a נשואין nisuin
type of relationship. So the ר"ן Ran says according to this position,
it would be without the father. According to this idea that it's
paying מזונות mezonos and it's like a נשואין, nisuin, then it's with...
then he's treated as a בעל, ba'al, not just as an ארוס,
arus, and he would be doing it even without the father. Okay?
So we have two questions now in the משנה. Mishnah. One is
when the יבם yavam is able to be מפר meifer according to
those that he can, is he מפר meifer because it's similar to
אירוסין, eirusin, which is suggested in the משנה Mishnah because of the
comparison to somebody who marries a woman taken לו מן השמים lo
min hashamayim etc., seems to all be like a type of קידושין
kiddushin type of a discussion. Is it like אירוסין eirusin and it's
only with the father? Or is it like נשואין nisuin and it's
by himself, which certainly seems to be the case here when the
גמרא Gemara is saying in the case of two, the reason to
select one over the other... the reason that one is identified is
because he's paying the food bills and it's like already נשואין. nisuin.
Okay? That seems to be independent of the father. Let's take a
look now at the עמוד ב'. amud beis. תנן. Tnan. תנן רבי
אליעזר. Tnan Rabbi Eliezer. ומה אשה שקנה לעצמו הרי הוא מפר נדריה.
Umah ishah shekanah le'atzmo harei hu meifer nedareha. So now it's going
through exactly that line in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, a woman that he was קונה
koneh for himself, he annuls the vows. אשה שקנו לו מן השמים
אינו דין שיפר נדריה. Ishah shekanu lo min hashamayim eino din sheyafer
nedareha. Okay, so how much more so for someone... Now, we want
to say how does this fit into the way we suggested reading
the משנה? Mishnah? אי דעשה בה מאמר, Ei de'asah bah ma'amar, if
it's according to רב אמי's Rav Ami read that he was עושה
מאמר, oseh ma'amar, that's the whole scenario we're talking about, so קנה
לעצמו
קנה לעצמו הוא. kanah le'atzmo kanah le'atzmo hu. So what... why do
you say to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, "Oh רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
this is a stronger because, you know, this was מן השמים min
hashamayim as opposed to a case of קנה לעצמו?" kanah le'atzmo? If
the case we're talking about was יבום yibum plus מאמר, ma'amar, this
case is not just מן השמים, min hashamayim, this case was also
קנה לעצמו. kanah le'atzmo. So, right, it's being described inaccurately. So that's
not really such a problem because that just makes this case all
the stronger. Right? So the גמרא Gemara says fine, קנה לעצמו על
ידי שמים. kanah le'atzmo al yedei shamayim. Okay, fine, he helped him,
right? He's like, "Look, this case is מן השמים min hashamayim (parenthetically
plus he also did his own thing on top of this), and
that should be stronger than a guy who just did it himself."
All right, so that wasn't such a question. All right, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: תפשוט דבעי מאמר דבעי רבא. Tifshot
deba'ei ma'amar deba'ei Rava. You can conclude... if that's the read of
the משנה Mishnah as מאמר, ma'amar, then you should be able to
use this to resolve the question that רבא Rava raised. What's the
question that רבא Rava
raised? מאמר לבית שמאי אירוסין עושה או נישואין עושה? Ma'amar le-Beis Shammai
eirusin oseh o nisuin oseh? Assuming that מאמר ma'amar for בית שמאי
Beis Shammai is קנין גמור, kinyan gamur, what state does it bring
it to? Does it bring it to אירוסין eirusin or bring it
to נשואין? nisuin? And you should say why does it bring it
to נשואין? nisuin? I mean, מאמר ma'amar is an act of קידושין,
kiddushin, הרי את מקודשת. harei at mekudeshes. But the fact that it's
an act of קידושין kiddushin that's building on the pre... you know,
a relationship that's ready to materialize and to actualize through this act
of sex, right, you know, without even any דעת da'as for that
and so on, so maybe that actually raises it to the level
of נשואין nisuin and it's not just אירוסין, eirusin, it's not just
an act of קידושין, kiddushin, right? So what is its status? הנפקא
מינה Hanafka mina would be, right, does he give her מזונות mezonos
after מאמר, ma'amar, all the other questions about are they halachically defined
as נשואה nesuah after מאמר? ma'amar? So that was רבא's Rava question.
So how are we going to resolve it?
תפשוט, Tifshot, let's resolve נשואין עושה, nisuin oseh, that מאמר ma'amar actually
makes her like a נשואין. nisuin. How do we resolve that?
So
what do you mean that the יבם yabam can do it? What
about the father?
Now this גמרא Gemara is saying that if you read the משנה,
mishnah, the משנה mishnah says יפר יפר יפר, yafer yafer yafer, the
משנה mishnah doesn't mention the father, right? I raised that question in
the משנה: mishnah: is there also a father here and so on?
But the גמרא Gemara here is assuming that the משנה mishnah sounds
like if the יבם yabam is doing it, he's doing it by
himself. So therefore it's assuming that those that say a יבם yabam
has a status, he has a status like a בעל, ba'al, like
נישואין. nisuin. Okay?
So we can therefore say, since—I know what you could say, we'll
see it in a minute—but assuming that the משנה mishnah doesn't mention
the father, anybody who says the father-in-law can do it, does it
like a בעל, ba'al, does it like נישואין. nisuin. So this should
resolve the idea that if you do מאמר, maamar, it raises it
to the status of נישואין, nisuin, because that seems to be what's
going on in the משנה, mishnah, that they're like נישואין. nisuin. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. The גמרא Gemara says no, אמר רב
יצחק אמר רב אמי: Amar Rav Yitzchak, Amar Rav Ami: יפר יפר
בשותפות. yafer yafer beshutfut. No, יפר yafer doesn't mean by himself. It
means together with the father. It means he has the status of
an ארוס, arus, doesn't mean he has the status of a בעל.
ba'al. Alright? So we're back to the indeterminate, we'll say indeterminate, which
of the brothers-in-law is assuming the indeterminate meaning of the משנה. mishnah.
For
when the יבם yabam has the status, is it by himself like
a בעל, ba'al, or is it like an ארוס arus together with
the father? That's not clear from the משנה. mishnah. According to the
idea that he's חייב מזונות chayav mezonot and it makes him like
a בעל, ba'al, then obviously it would be by himself. According to
the idea that מאמר maamar is קונה קניין גמור koneh kinyan gamur
according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, then it's an open question whether
according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai that would make him like an
ארוס arus and he does it with the father or like a
בעל ba'al and he does it by himself. תניא נמי הכי Tanya
nami hachi de'Rav Ami. We taught like רב אמי, Rav Ami, this
idea that we're dealing with a case of
מאמר. maamar. How do you know? Where do we have? This here's
the ברייתא, braita, the תוספתא: Tosefta:
שומרת יבם בין יבם אחד בין שני יבמים, shomeret yabam bein yabam
echad bein shnei yevanim, a woman is waiting for ייבום, yibum, whether
one brother or two. רבי אליעזר
אומר יפר. Rabbi Eliezer omer yafer. רבי יהושע אומר לאחד ולא לשניים.
Rabbi Yehoshua omer le'echad velo lishnayim. Rabbi Eliezer says fine, Rabbi Yehoshua
says only if there's one, not if there's two. רבי עקיבא אומר
לא לאחד ולא לשניים, Rabbi Akiva omer lo le'echad velo lishnayim, not
one, not two. אמר רבי אליעזר: Amar Rabbi Eliezer: ומה אם אשה
שאין לו חלק בה עד שלא תבא לרשותו. u'mah im isha she'ein
lo chelek bah ad shelo tavo lereshuto. So Rabbi Eliezer says to
Rabbi Akiva, I don't understand this. A normal woman, she has absolutely
no relationship to him until he actually marries her, right? She's halachically
a complete stranger, and then he does an act of קידושין. kiddushin.
And that woman that
משבאת לרשותו, mishebat'a lereshuto, once there's an act of—now you have to
understand, the ר"ן Ran says משבאת לרשותו, mishebat'a lereshuto, I would naturally
assume to mean נשואה, nesuah, right? But the ר"ן Ran says if
it were נשואה, nesuah, it would say נכנסה לרשותו. nichnesah lereshuto. You
have to excuse me, I don't see a big difference between the
word נכנס nichnas and בא. ba. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara is
choosing to read this that we're talking about קידושין, kiddushin, okay? So
normal woman, he has no relationship to her until he does the
act of קידושין. kiddushin. משבאת לרשותו mishebat'a lereshuto once he does the
act of
קידושין, kiddushin, ומה אם אשה שאין
לו חלק בה עד שלא תבא לרשותו
משבאת לרשותו נמסרו לו, u'mah im isha she'ein lo chelek bah ad
shelo tavo lereshuto mishebat'a lereshuto nimseru lo, she's fully his wife and
therefore he's able to go ahead and do הפרה. hafara. אשה שיש
לו חלק בה עד שלא תבא
לרשותו, Isha sheyesh lo chelek bah ad shelo tavo lereshuto, the sister-in-law
that he has a connection to—there's a מצווה mitzvah ייבום, yibum, there's
a זיקה—before zika he actually goes ahead and brings it to the
next step. So משבאת לרשותו mishebat'a lereshuto eino din sheyimeiru lo? How
much more so should he have that power once she's באה לרשותו?
bat'a lereshuto? Now what's באה לרשותו? bat'a lereshuto? So if באה לרשותו
bat'a lereshuto means he does the act of ייבום, yibum, then we
can't be talking about that. If he does the act of ייבום,
yibum, she's his wife, right? Nobody would be debating it. So what's
the stage after זיקה zika before ייבום yibum where she's more באה
לרשותו? bat'a lereshuto? מאמר. Maamar. Okay, so that's how we know we're
talking about מאמר. maamar. That he had already a relationship with this
woman before he did anything, meaning זיקה. zika. Now that he's done
something, how much more so, so it must be he's done מאמר.
maamar. Okay, because she still has to—can't be his wife. Okay, so
therefore how much more so should he have that ability? So that
shows that we're talking about a case of מאמר. maamar. So אמר
לו Amar lo, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva. so Rabbi Akiva said back
to him, לאו, lav, if you said בקידושין bekiddushin שקנה הוא לעצמו,
shekanah hu le'atzmo, what he did himself, שכשם שאין לו חלק בה.
shekeshem she'ein lo chelek bah.
It's true that before he did the קידושין, kiddushin, he had no
connection to her, but nobody else had a connection to her either.
And more to the point, after he does the קידושין, kiddushin, then
actually nobody not only doesn't have one but nobody can have one.
The קידושין kiddushin closes out everybody else.
תאמר באשה Tomar be'isha שהקנו לו מן השמים shehiknu lo min hashamayim
שכשם שיש לו עמה חלק. shekeshem sheyesh lo imah chelek. In the
case of ייבום, yibum, the same way he has a connection
to her, so... the brother also has a connection to her, and
presumably even after מאמר, ma'amar, the brother can go in and do
יבום. Yibbum. Okay, he's not supposed to, but he can. So you
can't compare it to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva It's true there's more
of a connection here, but there's somebody else in the picture. So
אמר לו amar lo רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, as רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua said to him, עקיבא, זו היא בשני יבמין. Akiva, zu hi
bishnei yevamin. This is all a repeat of the משנה. Mishnah. So
עקיבא, Akiva, what you're saying is true if there are two brother-in-laws,
so you could say it's not exclusive and therefore neither of them
have even after מאמר ma'amar this guy doesn't have a נפולה nefulah
status. But מה אתה משיב ביבם אחד, mah attah meshiv b'yavam echad,
what do you say if there's only one? אמר ליה, amar leh,
he says back to him, פום חלשתא יבם אחד או שני יבמין,
pum hachlashta yavam echad o shnei yevamin, בין עשה מאמר בין לא
עשה מאמר. bein asah ma'amar bein lo asah ma'amar. He said, I
don't care, one יבם, yavam, two יבמין, yevamin, yes מאמר, ma'amar, no
מאמר, ma'amar, none of that matters to me. Even if it's only
one יבם yavam and he did מאמר, ma'amar, it would not be
enough. Why? Okay, why not? One יבם yavam and he did מאמר,
ma'amar, הוא בא לו מן השמים, hu ba lo min ha-shamayim, yes,
and he did his מאמר, ma'amar, there's nobody else in the picture.
Why not? So he says, וכשאר דברים כן נדרים, u'kesha'ar devarim ken
nedarim, because just like everything else, נדרים nedarim is no different. What
does that mean, just like everything else? So the גמרא Gemara is
going to say, just like when it comes, for example, to adultery,
she's not yet fully his wife. If she were to sleep with
another man, it would not be an act of adultery. So no
matter how strong this connection is, there's זיקה, zikah, there's מאמר, ma'amar,
there's no other person around, nevertheless, she's not his wife yet.
What about the חיוב מזונות? chiyyub mezonot?
He doesn't, he doesn't have that, okay, it's only once there's
a חיוב מזונות. chiyyub mezonot. And therefore, and therefore, I don't care
how much they're in a relationship, before it gets to the stage
of קידושין Kiddushin of אשת איש eshet ish and so on, he
cannot be מיפר. mefer. So בלשון הזה אמר בן עזאי, bilshon ha-zeh
amar Ben Azzai, with this language Ben Azzai responded to this debate,
חבלו לך בן עזאי, chavalo l'cha Ben Azzai, woe to you Ben
Azzai, שלא שמשת את רבי עקיבא, she-lo shimashat et Rabbi Akiva, that
you did not attend to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's and you could've
learned from him. Of course, it's pretty funny because רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva's punchline, A, it's not even so clear, right? It sounds like
they have a good case, you know? There's only one guy, he
did מאמר, ma'amar, he did all of this, and then רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva response is very terse, it's not clear how he's responding
back. So it's like Ben Azzai is like saying like, oh my
god, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's is so
brilliant, if I
had attended him, then I
would've understood
what he meant by
this, like the answer's a little bit too terse, you know, I
wish I understood more what he was actually answering and saying there.
And if I had attended to him more, I could've understood it
better. Okay, that's not normally how the ראשונים Rishonim explain it, they
like say like, he was blown away by רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
brilliance and woe that I didn't work with him. Anyway, fine. So
that was a debate in the משנה. Mishnah. And now the גמרא
Gemara just spells out, מאי טעמא כותיה דרבי אמי, mai ta'amei kevatiah
d'Rabbi Ami, how does this support רבי
אמי? Rabbi Ami? דתני, de-tani, בין עשה מאמר בין לא עשה מאמר.
bein asah ma'amar bein lo asah ma'amar. Okay, because רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva's says, I don't care, yes מאמר, ma'amar, no מאמר, ma'amar, etc.,
which shows that we were talking about a case of מאמר, ma'amar,
that was on the table, that that was part of the conversation,
right? אימא סיפא, ima seifa, even clearer from the beginning, מרישא, me-reisha,
דתני משנכנסה לרשותו נגמרה לו, de-tani mishenichnesah lirshuto nigmarah lo,
right? He says that he says look, in this case when
it's נכנסה לרשותו... nichnesah lirshuto... that
actually is our משנה, Mishnah, right?
No, no, it was there.
I don't think they've ever used
that.
Oh, we did, it says משבאה. mishebata. You're right, actually, that was
the ר"ן's Ran's point, that it was באה bata not נכנסה. nichnesah.
But right, but it says in this case of אשה שיש לו
חלק בה, ishah she-yesh lo chelek bah, משבאת לרשותו אין הדין שתגמור
לו? mishebata lirshuto ein hadin she-tigmora lo?
So what is, so it says that she was באה לרשותו, ba'ah
lirshuto, this יבמה. yevamah. How is she באה לרשותו ba'ah lirshuto and
still not his wife, right? So ואי לאו קדיש, v'ee lav kaddish,
מה נגמרה לו? mah nigmarah lo?
If there was no קידושין, Kiddushin, right, what does it mean? You
know, what does it mean באה לרשותו נגמרה לו, ba'ah lirshuto nigmarah
lo, etc.? It's clear from this case that we were talking about
a woman who was a sister-in-law, he had a relationship, חלק בה,
chelek bah, and then there was some other act that made it
even more, you know, sort of designated to him and fully and,
you know, and excluded the other brother. Okay, so clearly we were
talking about a case that there was מאמר, ma'amar, and that can
help us explain how it is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
that one brother is in a position although there are two brothers
and in theory the other brother could do it, but when one
did מאמר, ma'amar, he's in that position. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, קא פשיט מיניה דכשעשה בה מאמר. ka pashit mineih d'keshe-asah
bah ma'amar.
So therefore you can learn from this, this is that you can
learn from this that it's a case of מאמר. ma'amar. Now, let's
just finish, מאי mai and what is ומה כשאר דברים כן נדרים,
u'mah k'sha'ar devarim ken nedarim, what's רבי עקיבא's response? Okay, once you
say there's only one יבם yavam and it's זיקה zikah and it's
מאמר, ma'amar, what's his response so then, yeah, why can't he do
הפרה? ha'afarah? דתני אמר רבא הכי קתני, de-tani amar Rava hachi katan,
אי אתה מודה שאין חייבין סקילה ee attah modeh she-ein chayavin sekilah
כנערה המאורסה. k'na'arah ha-me'urasah.
You would admit that if she were to sleep with another man,
that she wouldn't get stoned, it wouldn't be an act of adultery.
Okay, so therefore just like in other laws נדרים nedarim is no
different. She's not fully מקודשת *mekudeshet*, no matter how strong, how much
there's a מצוה *mitzvah* here to do יבום *yibum* and there's a
relationship, she's not fully אשת איש *eshet ish*, so therefore he can't
do הפרה *hafara*. רב אשי מתני הכא נמי דיקא *Rav Ashi matni
hacha nami dika*, אין יבמה גמורה לאיש כשם שארוסה גמורה לאיש *ein
yevama gmura l'ish keshem she'arusa gmura l'ish*. And that's actually the last
line of our משנה *mishna* as well. He says the יבמה *yevama*
is not fully this man's wife the same way a normal woman
is, and therefore רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says, I don't care how
much you hold of זיקה *zika* and מאמר *maamar* and the whole
thing, unless it's really אשת איש *eshet ish*, you cannot do הפרה
*hafara*. Okay, are we now even more than the מצפה *metzapeh*?
It actually is interesting how quick some of these סוגיות *sugyos* go.